given all of the contenders that are out
if this isn't Evan
Singleton's best opportunity to get on
the podium or actually stake a claim for
a title I don't know what year is Sarah
rainbow hit the heaviest raw total ever
by a woman at
775 kg only took seven lifts to get
there it was a disputed call there was a
Fallout author effectively said I will
never do a giants live event again and
we haven't seen him since
hey folks welcome back to strength
weekly the show that keeps you up to
date on everything you need to know from
around the barbell game and some stuff
you probably don't need to know but
we're going to say anyway I am one of
your Intrepid hosts David Thomas to the
intrep intrepidus host is Phil Blackman
Phil how you feeling today bro I'm
feeling so good we're on the cusp of
world's strongest man competition and
I'm living for it okay well you know
what I did not oh fun fact folks uh a
couple years ago some folks from the
barbend team went to World's Strongest
Man uh to do media coverage and they
asked if I wanted a volunteer shirt
because I wasn't going to be there I
said yes I told them my size was medium
turns out World's Strongest Man
volunteer shirts start at
large should have seen that one coming
anyway we're going to give our World's
Strongest Man predictions or rather
Phil's going to give his World's
Strongest Man predictions cuz no one
cares what I have to say other things on
today's show include hop through boron's
Competition schedule and a little
reminder as to why it doesn't include
world's strongest man this year even
though he has returned to Pro strongman
we are also chatting about alltime world
record power lifting total from Sarah
rainbow and
finally how strong are weightlifters
like if you had to you know if they had
to Squad against powerlifters how are
they doing well we have a little bit of
insight from one upand cominging
American weightlifter who just might be
a prospect for the next Olympic quad we
will talk about that but this episode
folks I'm going to tell you right now
it's heavily about world strongest man
um Phil the World's Strongest Man roster
for 2024 and by the way world's
strongest man kicks off in just about a
week from the publication of this
episode few roster changes this year
Martin's Le's out as he recovers from a
sciatica called injury Alexi novakov out
as he recovers from an injury sustained
at Europe's Strongest Man haur Bon out
for polit what's called political reason
that's reason Brian Shaw out because he
retired happy trails to Brian Shaw Matos
Kish Kowski out
so so funny funny we talked about last
episode uh the the roster was in flux
right there was all of these uh big
names that were pulling out due to
injury novakov 2020 world Strongest Man
L's 2019 world Strongest Man KES Kowski
two-time runner up at the world
strongest man Brian Shaw for the first
time in almost two decades not at
World's Strongest Man because he is done
with competitive strongman so a lot has
gone on and among the things that has
gone on that has flown under the radar
is this is going to be the first
competition that Trey Mitchell is
returning to competition after his
Achilles uh injury so we thought that he
was not going to be ready to come back
but apparently he is because he is on
the roster he is expected to be
competing in Myrtle Beach six months six
months for an Achilles recovery that's a
short amount of time I mean we might
have a Jerry Rice situation here he's
coming back same season basically coming
back same season if I mean you know
maybe he's not going to be as strong on
the movements that require legs deadlift
all that stuff but like May maybe he can
get away I don't know I I Trey Mitchell
is a wild card in this one let's but
let's talk about it Trey Mitchell is a
wild card we're just going to put him in
the Wild Card category he's been a
Podium Contender for the last handful of
years but now he's coming in with an
injury on the flip side of that Luke
stalman a Mainstay at the world
Strongest Man finals and getting into
fifth place is a would is a great finish
for him in the past couple of years if
he could do it right his range is
usually in the bottom half of the finals
but he's usually a finals Contender this
year with all of the fallouts between
L's KES Kowski novakov Shaw bjon they're
not they're not around a lot of slots
open up and he has a lot of momentum
because he just won the Europe's
strongest man for the second time so
most of the momentum is on Luke stman
side going into this competition but
let's talk about who I think the real
spotlights are on in this competition if
you had to pin me down it's a two-horse
race for the top of the podium between
former two-time world Strongest Man Tom
stolman and Mitchell Hooper you would
argue Mitchell Hooper is probably the
favorite he hasn't dropped a contest in
a year like dude seems unbeatable at
this position but uh if anybody can come
back stolman now knows what it's like to
have the title he now knows what it's
like to lose the title and now he's
chasing not defending the mindset for
chasing versus defending is different
but those are my two my top two front
guys here's the guy that I would watch
given all of the contenders that are out
if this isn't Evan
Singleton's best opportunity to get on
the podium or actually stake a claim for
a title I don't know what year is I
don't know what year is not going to
have those other top guys trying to
claim spots and Singleton who was in the
top half of the finals last year if he
can temper his aggression in the early
stages and not wear himself out too thin
over the course of a long event if he
can tidy that up and then just come in
and execute a game plan he is my guy who
I would put on the podium with Mitch
with stman and Hooper and if he can have
the event of his life when the
opportunity strikes Lenny come up in the
clutch I think Singleton is the guy who
could you know be the upset win if
everything goes according to plan and he
you know he he executes properly Phil
now I know you don't get predictions out
of context context is very important you
are a consumate journalist but let's
give some predictions out of context who
are your top five in order from first to
fifth finishers predictions for this
year's world's strongest man I think
Mitchell Hooper defends the crown I
think Tom stman gets his second silver
in a row uh which you know I mean Legacy
to be had there I think Evan Singleton's
going to make his first Podium I think
he's going to score bronze I'm going to
put Pavo C yaka in fourth based on the
event structure that we know for the
finals which involves a lot of cardio
and then I'm going to say Matthew rag is
going to come in in fifth he had a
really big performance last year I think
the roster has uh leveled him up as long
as he can hold on to the cardio
alongside caka I think he's going to
handle the heavy events really well
Amazing Phil I appreciate that um I just
want to say we don't criticize Phil if
he gets things wrong but he gets things
right more often than not one of the
first by the way to call Mitchell Hooper
uh a World's Strongest Man Contender
about two years ago so Phil Blackman I
really appreciate your expert takes um I
can't wait to be watching the event
you'll be on the ground covering it live
correct I will be working with coverage
happening live in Myrtle Beach all right
just folks remember to tune in to
World's Strongest Man May 1st through
the 5th it does not stream live it is on
a TV delay but we will be bringing you
all the coverage from live on the ground
via barbett and our social media
channels Phil let's move on let's talk
about Hof Thor Bon Hur bornon is the
2018 world's strongest man he's won
basically every major contest you can
win in strongman at least every major
contest that existed when he was
competing right Arnold strongman classic
Champion uh has deadlifted more than any
human in history is back to competitive
strongman after taking a break to
compete in boxing and then in
powerlifting um recovering from injury
yeah recovering from injury made his
return this year to competitive
strongman had really good performances
I'd say say probably a little better
than we expected at the Arnold strongman
Classic in Columbus and also at the UK
version I think he he looked a little
better than we thought he would after
that many years off of pro strongman uh
what does this competition schedule look
like for the remainder of the year yeah
I wanted to say this is the the the one
moment where I have been got we've been
got David hawor exceeded my expectations
coming back to his first strongman event
after all that time off by a wide margin
I did not have him I did not think he
would be contending for a Podium at any
point he was contending against Hooper
for the podium for the majority of the
event he actually won the opening event
the Elephant bar deadlift of course like
who else is going to beat him in that he
clearly had enough in the tank it looked
like he might have been able to crack
the world record but he saved himself
because he wanted to do well in the
competition but like you know history
might have been different if he called
for a record weight on the Elephant Bar
it it looked like it would have been no
problem for him really really impressive
and now he's coming back we know what
his schedule is for the rest of 2024
well let's uh give a rundown on that
schedule kicks off with Iceland's
strongest man the 2024 I strongest man
he is a 10-time champion at that event
by the way a 10 time champion at
Iceland's strongest man um that's gonna
be the next event he competes in by the
way Iceland's strongest man Iceland's a
country of about 300,000 is people but
this is like a top eight strong Pro like
top eight strong man event in the world
because there are so many great
strongman competitors from Iceland like
it's disproportionate it's insane like
if you're one of the if you're the top
if you're the Iceland strongest man
you're likely one of the world's
strongest men it's just been that and
it's been that way for like 50 years by
the way like since the the Advent of pro
strongman absolutely insane so that's
his next competition and then his uh
followup competition after that is the
2024 strongest man on Earth which some
people might know formerly as the shaw
Classic this will be his first time
competing there that's Brian Shaw's
event and that's usually a static
strength focused event or more closer to
what you would see like at an Arnold
Classic and things like that it's skewed
towards the static heavier guys which
means that he should excel in that event
so expect him to do very well there and
then he closes the year with the 2024
strong man Invitational pretty good
looking schedule of events for hofor and
his return to Pro strongman for the rest
of the year one that's missing World's
Strongest Man Phil give us a quick
primer we don't got to get crazy
political but let's get a little
political here uh why does he not
compete in world strongest man because
as a former Champion he should qualify
he should be able to compete he should
be able to show up and win he won in
2018 he should be able to show up and
compete he kind of has a lifetime
invitation why won't we see him at world
strongest man this year yeah lifetime
invitation for any former world
Strongest Man winner you could see
Magnus for Magnuson come back and if he
wanted to Big Z if he wanted to come
back he could do that they could do that
because they are champions they likely
wouldn't make it at qualifying stage but
it would be great to see them anyway so
yeah the reason for hawthor not
competing at the world's strongest man
it's a giants live event and there was a
falling out back when there was the
controversy during the 2017 2018 World
strongest man era a single rep in a
viking press was the difference between
Eddie Hall winning in 2017 and ha Thor
coming in second and since then it was a
disputed call there was a Fallout about
that call then there was document and
coverage of like what actually went down
he said she said style stuff hathor
effectively said I will never do a
giants live event again and hence uh by
giants live it pretty much means for the
most part World's Strongest Man and we
haven't seen him since and it is
unlikely that we will see it until a
bridge is mended whatever bridge that
looks like in the actual no of the
people who know specifically as to what
happened but that's the the the short
and skinny of it is that's it falling
out back in 2017 2018 and we haven't
seen him well love short and skinny
because Pro strongman competitors are
usually not either of those things so
Phil appreciate that I think it was a
very diplomatic way to kind of give
folks a little rundown of of what we had
what we what we know and again we're on
the outside looking in it's a little bit
he said she said um so fun fact uh the
the thing that revolved around that was
a viking press rep and you know what's
coming back in the 2024 world Strongest
Man the Viking press the Viking press
guess it the Viking press will always
have that air around it at World's
Strongest Man which is why I'm so
excited for it
all right let's move over to the world
of powerlifting Sarah rainbow at the
2024 World raw powerlifting Federation
Australia lesten Toyota Showdown sure I
might be butchering that the lesten
Toyota Showdown Sarah rainbow hit the
heaviest raw total ever by a woman she
competes a super heavyweight at
775 kilograms only took seven lifts to
get there her performance on the day
only took two Squad attempts 285 kilos
and then finished with 315 kilos good
lift
all three bench press attempts uh were
made finished at
177.52 two deadlift attempts finished
with 282.30
but is able to come away with the
heaviest total and you got to think that
she and her coach had that planned out
because she only took seven attempts she
took the exact attempts she needed to
come away with that alltime world record
total I don't really have anything else
here to say except for good job Sarah
rainbow like holy cow yeah hell of a
performance I I want to just note for uh
the additional detail that this was a
raw with WPS competition that she
competed in so this is the heaviest raw
with wraps I mean that doesn't change
the deadlift but it does change the
squat but 775 kilograms uh the the
standings as it is now 775 was 2 and2
kilos heavier than the previous alltime
world record which was held by April
Matisse at 772 A2 and then you have to
you have a a drop off of 20 kilos before
you get to Jessica Springer uh in the
third heaviest ever so 775 is the new
mark all time to beat raw with W wraps
uh on the women's side hell of a
performance and I mean wear the crown
well wear the crown well I mean again we
don't really have anything like
controversial to say here
is that raw with wraps is different than
like raw with sleeves wraps you're going
to see folks squat a bit more that's
just the way it is wraps give you give
you extra kilos generally for most
people uh but you know great job Sarah
right I me this just this just an upbeat
positive segment there's no there's not
controversy here the lists look good no
one got angry on the platform no one
tried to throw a squat rack at the
judges that we know of good job Sarah
rainbow that's the takeaway here all
right let's keep we keep squatting but
we'll talk about weightlifter Scots
Miranda Oli of the United States is
still a junior lifter recently put up a
three times body weight squat now
weightlifters don't compete in the back
squat but we always wonder how would
weightlifters do if they did compete in
the back squat obviously different style
of squatting they tend to squat High bar
it tends to have more carryover to the
Olympic lifts to snatch cleaning jerk
some do squat low bar actually uh but
most squat High bar it's not a tested
lift and weightlifting it's not the
snatch of the cleaning jerk where
Miranda's 19 years old she squatted 180
kgrs it's nearly 400 lb just under 400
lb in training she generally competes as
a 59 kilo weightlifter right so it's
just a little bit above body weight
competition body weight she probably
trains a little bit above comp uh
competition body weight like most people
do Phil how would this
squat in her approximate body weight
categories in powerlifting they're not a
direct translation how would this squat
stack up to the world records four
lifters roughly her age and roughly her
body weight in powerlifting I'm so happy
you asked so let's say she was competing
in the 60 kgr category in a sanctioned
powerlifting event if we were to look in
the open category not the junior we'll
get there in a second but let's say it
was in the open category that she was
like my hand is in the
ring the top three alltime squats in the
60 kilogram category uh Mariana
gasparian 230 kilograms alltime Ro
record if anybody touches that in our
lifetimes uh what a blessing that would
be otherwise it's Susan Salazar at 197
half second all time third all time is
Andrea Armstrong at
195 so that's the open category so she's
15 C 15 kilos off of tying the third
heaviest all-time open squat okay that's
pretty impressive for a 19-year-old on
the own let's talk about where she would
stack not even training the squad
specifically the squad is an accessory
exercise an accessory exercise if she
were to compete in a sanctioned event I
want let's let's play this game David
where do you think her 180 kilogram
squat if she was at competition body
weight of 60 kilograms where would it
stack up in the uh in her age category
in juniors te 18 and 19 um so I mean
we're in 10 within 10 kilos here and by
the way this is a training squat this
was just like she probably did this
after like snatches and cleaning jerks
for the day so here's the cool here's
and here's the cool the coolest stat I
think of her 180 kilo squat if she
competed in sanction power lifting now
at the 60 kgam class at in her age group
which would be teens 18 and 19 in that
category she would have set the alltime
world record for the squat by 7 and a
half kilograms the heaviest squat in
teen 18 to 19 is 172 and A5 it's Daniela
Flores from that she set in September of
2022 and uh this 180 kilogram it would
have been over that by a margin that's
amazing and I I I just want to say that
powerlifting Junior in powerlifting goes
up to usually 23 years old Junior in
weightlifting goes up to 20 years old so
if you subdivide that into like teens
you get you get different subdivisions
of weight categories right so like a
junior world record for powerlifting
could be like a 22y old by the way
whereas a junior record for
weightlifting is normally someone who's
under 20 years old just to clarify the
third heaviest all time in the junior
category is 183 kgr so she's three kilos
off from hitting the third heaviest all
time in J in the junior category which
goes up to 23 so suffice to say all this
all this accumulates to culminates to uh
this 180 kilogram squat is insane that's
what it that's what it comes down to
David it's insane well I think let's
look at is recent International
competition history she finished in
fourth place at the 2021 youth World
Championships at 55 kilos body weight
she finished in second place at the 2022
Pan-American junior championships at 49
kilos body weight actually went down in
body weight at the 2023 Junior World
Championship she finished in fourth
place at 59 kilos body weight which is
roughly where she competes now so she is
an elite level lifter in on the
international stage the think about
Junior athletes athletes this age they
make progress quickly she is definitely
someone I had my eyes on for the next
Olympic quad now what's the next Olympic
quad well we have the Paris Olympics
coming up later this year we roughly
know who the women are gonna be on the
US team for weightlifting right it's
gonna be Olivia Reeves it's G to be
Jordan D Cruz is going to be uh Mary
Tyson Lin but for the next quad Los
Angeles weightlifting Los Angeles in
2028 who's gonna compete we don't know
right I think a really great example is
Olivia Reeves didn't come out of nowhere
but made such good
progress as a junior as a youth and
Junior lifter of the last quad she
basically bumped out the prospects we
thought we thought it was gonna be like
Kate Viber we thought it was gonna be
Maddie Rogers right we thought it was
gonna be maybe Meredith allwine Olivia
ree Lea frogged all three of those
lifters for the spot in Paris I have my
eyes on Miranda as a Potential Prospect
for the Los Angeles Olympics I think
there are a lot of really young
promising lifters uh Youth and Junior
lifters in the American system right now
I'm just giving my way to early
prediction that we should keep our eyes
on her as a potential Olympic Prospect
four years from now in Los Angeles which
if you're 19 years old four years is a
lot of time to make progress you can be
in a very different lifter right if
you're if you're young if you're one of
these lifter under 25 so I just wanted
to use this as an opportunity to talk
about strength to talk about
weightlifters versus powerlifters talk
about how weightlifters can make quite
good powerlifters if they only competed
in the squat sometimes and also to talk
about hey you know we have Paris coming
up but we're already looking ahead to
like 2028 I hope we're bring I hope
we're bringing you strength weekly in
2028 wouldn't that be fun Phil the next
time we talk it's gonna be prime time
for World's Strongest Man I mean it's
not going to be world's strongest man
but like we're giving the predictions
now so we have like a weak
buffer but boy howdy boy howdy is that
gonna be exciting boy howdy is that
gonna be exciting I mean if anything by
the time we talk next week who knows you
know five or six more of the strong men
on the roster get injured and withdraw
and we have a whole new roster were're
talking about based off how this year
has been has gone so far so yes we
should absolutely be getting hyped for
the world strongest man this year if
ever there was a time for an upset to
happen or for one of the guys that was
not like on the top of the radar like
they should be in their training cans
right now going this is the best
opportunity I have they should have a
plan for every single one of the events
they should have an idea of where they
should be on the leaderboard for each of
those events and what total points they
want after they reach the finals they
can get to the finals they should be
like I'm going to hit 51 points that's
where I stand that's my target at the
end of the thing and just execute just
execute that plan and they can actually
they you have a really good shot to
reach the podium because a lot of the
top contenders are out this year so like
let's see a new star do a have a star
performance titles are built upon
planning and execution until you plan
and execute your next championship I'm
David Thomas to joined by Phil Blackman
thanks for joining us here on strength
weekly